<sect1 xml:id="tutorials"><title>Tutorial</title>
	<!-- Introduction -->
	<para>
		This tutorial will show you how to create models with the MechatronicUML Tool Suite.
		To understand this tutorial you need to now what Mechatronic UML (MUML) is.
		The tutorial will not explain the features of MUML, so please look into the Tech Report (LINK)
		if you have any questions concerning MUML.
		To teach you how to use the MechatronicUML Tool Suite we will create all the required models of the following example.
	</para>
	<para>
		Let there be two robots called BeBots. One shall be the master and one the slave.
		The master BeBot has a task list and each task represents a target position the slave has to drive to.
		From this task list a task shall be sent to the slave BeBot and be executed by him.
		When the slave has finished the task within a given time, the master transmits the next one.
		If the slave fails executing the task in the given time, the same task will be sent again.
		For execution the slave shall know its current position.
		In this example we will abstract from engine control in the behavior of the BeBots.
	</para>
	<para>
		To implement this example in Fujaba models we will perform the following steps - as far as possible - gradually:
	</para>
	<itemizedlist mark='bullet'>
		<listitem>
			<para>
			Create a new project for this tutorial
			</para>
		</listitem>
		
		<listitem>
			<para>
			Create data types for storing positions and the task list
			</para>
		</listitem>
		
		<listitem>
			<para>
			Create Message Interfaces defining message types for the communication between the BeBots
			</para>
		</listitem>
		
		<listitem>
			<para>
			Create a Real-Time Coordination Protocol "Delegation" defining how the master and the
			slave BeBots can communicate using the Message Interfaces
			</para>
		</listitem>
		
		<listitem>
			<para>
			Create Real-Time Statecharts (RTSCs) defining the behavior of the roles of the delegation pattern
			</para>
		</listitem>
		
		<listitem>
			<para>
			Create an Atomic Component for the Software of the BeBots
			</para>
		</listitem>
		
		<listitem>
			<para>
			Create an Atomic Component for the position detection of the BeBots (abstracted as a GPS module)
			</para>
		</listitem>
		
		<listitem>
			<para>
			Create a Structured Component defining how a master resp. slave BeBot is constructed
			</para>
		</listitem>
		
		<listitem>
			<para>
			Create RTSCs defining the behavior of the components and the components’ ports
			</para>
		</listitem>
		
		<listitem>
			<para>
			Create a Component Instance Configuration to bind the whole example
			</para>
		</listitem>
		
		<listitem>
			<para>
			Finally we create a Deployment to allocate the defined software components to hardware nodes
			</para>
		</listitem>
		
	</itemizedlist>
	
	<!-- Step 1: Create a new project -->
	<sect2><title>Step 1: Create a new project</title>
		<para>
			Before we can start modeling the example, we need a project to work in.
			Click on "File --> New --> Other" as seen in the following screenshot:
			<figure id="img:step001">
				<mediaobject>
      				<imageobject>
 	     				<imagedata fileref="User Guide/images/tutorial/tutorialStep001.png" scale="120"/>
      				</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</figure>
			Select "Project" from the folder "General" and click "Next".
			<figure id="img:step002">
				<mediaobject>
      				<imageobject>
 	     				<imagedata fileref="User Guide/images/tutorial/tutorialStep002.png" scale="100"/>
      				</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</figure>
			Name the project "Fujaba_Tutorial" and click "Finish".
			You now have created an empty project that can be seen in the Project Explorer View.
		</para>
		<para>
			Now right click on the new project and select "New --> Other".
			Within the folder "Fujaba" select "Fujaba Model" and click "Next".
			Change the file name to "FujabaTutorial.fujaba" and click "Finish".
			Open the project "Fujaba_Tutorial" by double clicking.
			There you can see a file "FujabaTutorial.fujaba".
			This is the Fujaba model you created in the last step.
			Your window should look like this now:
			<figure id="img:step003">
				<mediaobject>
      				<imageobject>
 	     				<imagedata fileref="User Guide/images/tutorial/tutorialStep003.png" scale="120"/>
      				</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</figure>
			Now we can start defining the models described in the introduction.
		</para>
	</sect2>
	
	<!-- Step 2: Create Data Types -->
	<sect2><title>Step 2: Create Data Types</title>
		<para>
			First of all we need two array data types for this tutorial.
			The first type is called "XYPosition" and is an integer array with two
			entries for the x and y value of a position. 
			The second type is called "XYPositionArray" and is an array with ten
			entries of type "XYPosition" representing the task list of the master BeBot.
		</para>
		<para>
			To create these types right click onto the drawing surface of any diagram
			(here you only have the Message Interface diagram) and select
			"Fujaba --> Open Type Dialog", as seen in the next screenshot.
			<!-- opening the type dialog will be possible by right clicking on
			the Fujaba model in future -> this explanation should be changed then)-->
			<figure id="img:step006">
				<mediaobject>
      				<imageobject>
 	     				<imagedata fileref="User Guide/images/tutorial/tutorialStep006.png" scale="120"/>
      				</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</figure>
			A new dialog pops up. Here you can define your own array data types.
			For that, click on "Create". Now you can find a new type in the list.
			Click on it.In the lower part of the dialog you can change the properties.
			At this point we want to create the XYPosition type.
			Therefore, change the properties as follows:
			<itemizedlist mark='bullet'>
      			<listitem><para>
      				<emphasis role="bold">Cardinality:</emphasis> 2
      			</para></listitem>
      			<listitem><para>
      				<emphasis role="bold">Comment:</emphasis> x and y values of a position
      			</para></listitem>
      			<listitem><para>
      				<emphasis role="bold">Name:</emphasis> XYPosition
      			</para></listitem>
      			<listitem><para>
      				<emphasis role="bold">Type:</emphasis> Primitive Data Type INT
      			</para></listitem>
      		</itemizedlist>
      		The settings can also be seen in the following screenshot:
      		<figure id="img:step007">
				<mediaobject>
      				<imageobject>
 	     				<imagedata fileref="User Guide/images/tutorial/tutorialStep007.png" scale="100"/>
      				</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</figure>
			After this create the XYPositionArray type with the following properties:
			<itemizedlist mark='bullet'>
      			<listitem><para>
      				<emphasis role="bold">Cardinality:</emphasis> 10
      			</para></listitem>
      			<listitem><para>
      				<emphasis role="bold">Comment:</emphasis> an array of xy-positions
      			</para></listitem>
      			<listitem><para>
      				<emphasis role="bold">Name:</emphasis> XYPositionArray
      			</para></listitem>
      			<listitem><para>
      				<emphasis role="bold">Type:</emphasis> XYPosition
      			</para></listitem>
      		</itemizedlist>
      		Click "OK".
		</para>
	</sect2>
	
	<!-- Step 3: Create Message Interfaces -->
	<sect2><title>Step 3: Create Message Interfaces</title>
		<para>
			We need two Message Interfaces that define the interfaces
			for a coordination pattern that we generate in step 3.
			For that, right click on your "FujabaTutorial.fujaba" model and select
			"New --> Other". Within "Fujaba --> Diagrams" select "Messageinterface Diagram"
			and click "Next", as seen in the following screenshot:
			<figure id="img:step005">
				<mediaobject>
      				<imageobject>
 	     				<imagedata fileref="User Guide/images/tutorial/tutorialStep005.png" scale="100"/>
      				</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</figure>
			Change the file name to "delegation.messageinterface_diagram" and click  "Next".
			Make sure that the correct model is selected (FujabaTutorial.fujaba) and click "Finish".
			The generation of new models always works like this whereas you need to select another
			model than "Messageinterface Diagram" of course.
		</para>
		<para>
			The Message Interface diagram opens in a new tab.
			You can also find it within your project folder.
		</para>
		<para>
			Now we can start with our Message Interfaces.
			Open the file "delegation.messageinterface_diagram" and select "MessageInterface"
			within the palette on the right side of the editor.
			Click into the drawing surface and a new Message Interface will be created.
			Change the name to "Master2Slave" by selecting the interface and pressing F2 or
			double-clicking on the name of the interface.
			Changing the name of an element should always be possible this way.
			If not, you have to change the property "Name" within the Properties View
			(<ulink url="https://trac.cs.upb.de/mechatronicuml/wiki/FujabaTutorial#ThePropertiesView">
	   			--> How to use the Properties View
	   		</ulink>).
			Add a Message Type to the interface by selecting "MessageType" from the palette
			and clicking into the existing interface and name it "order".
			This message type needs a parameter. Hence click on "Parameter" and then on the
			message type "order". Name the parameter "target".
			Now it is the first time we need to change a property.
			For that click on the parameter "target".
			Within the Properties View you find the property "Type".
			Select "Array Data Type XYPosition" to set the type
			(<ulink url="https://trac.cs.upb.de/mechatronicuml/wiki/FujabaTutorial#ThePropertiesView">
	   			--> How to use the Properties View
	   		</ulink>).
			Your diagram should look like this now:
			<figure id="img:step008">
				<mediaobject>
	      			<imageobject>
	 	     			<imagedata fileref="User Guide/images/tutorial/tutorialStep008.png" scale="120"/>
	      			</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</figure>
			Now create a second Message Interface with the following properties analogously:
			<itemizedlist mark='bullet'>
	      		<listitem><para>
	   				<emphasis role="bold">Name:</emphasis> Slave2Master
	   			</para></listitem>
	   			<listitem><para>
	      			<emphasis role="bold">MessageType:</emphasis> "fail" and "done" without any paramters
	      		</para></listitem>
	      	</itemizedlist>
	      	You probably should save your work now. The Message Interface diagram should look like this:
	      	<figure id="img:step009">
				<mediaobject>
	      			<imageobject>
	 	     			<imagedata fileref="User Guide/images/tutorial/tutorialStep009.png" scale="120"/>
	      			</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</figure>
		</para>
	</sect2>
	
	<!-- Step 4: Create a Real-Time Coordination Protocol "Delegation" -->
	<sect2><title>Step 4: Create a Real-Time Coordination Protocol "Delegation"</title>
		<para>
			To define how the master and the slave BeBots of our example can communicate
			we need to create a Real-Time Coordination Protocol.
			As said before we need a pattern named "Delegation".
			This pattern defines the coordination of how a master part delegates work to the slave part.
			Therefore, create a Pattern diagram analogously to the way of generating a Message Interface
			diagram with the name "delegation.pattern_diagram".
		</para>
		<para>
			In the editor that opens in a new tab we can now define Coordination Protocols.
			Click on "CoordinationProtocol" and then onto the drawing surface to add a new pattern.
			Change the name "pattern" to "Delegation" and the names "role1" and "role2" to "master"
			and "slave". At this moment your diagram should look like this:
			<figure id="img:step010">
			<mediaobject>
      			<imageobject>
 	     			<imagedata fileref="User Guide/images/tutorial/tutorialStep010.png" scale="120"/>
      			</imageobject>
			</mediaobject>
			</figure>
			Furthermore we need to set Message Interfaces for the roles that define which message
			types they can use for communication. For that click on the role "master".
			Within the category "Misc" you can find the properties
			"Receiver Message Interface" and "Sender Message Interface".
			As Receiver Message Interface select "Message Interface Slave2Master" and as Sender Message
			Interface select "Message Interface Master2Slave".
			Summarizing this means that the master BeBot can send messages of the message type
			order( target: XYPosition) and receive messages of the types fail() and done().
		</para>
		<para>
			For the role "slave" we also have to set these interfaces.
			As Receiver Message Interface select "Message Interface Master2Slave"
			and as Sender Message Interface select "Message Interface Slave2Master". 
			The assignments of the interfaces are vice versa to the master role,
			because it is the opposition of the communication.
		</para>
		<para>
			By setting these interfaces we defined our roles to be in-out-roles.
			That is shown by the two triangles on the inside of a role.
		</para>
		<para>
			When you now save your work, two red Xs appear at the roles.
			These Xs tell you that your model violates constraints of the Mechatronic UML.
			When you move the cursor to an X and wait a second a description pops up.
			At this point we did not set a behavior in form of a Real-Time Statechart for the roles.
			Therefore, we have to create two RTSCs describing the behavior first.
		</para>
		<para>
			At this point your Pattern diagram should look like this:
			<figure id="img:step011">
			<mediaobject>
      			<imageobject>
 	     			<imagedata fileref="User Guide/images/tutorial/tutorialStep011.png" scale="120"/>
      			</imageobject>
			</mediaobject>
			</figure>
		</para>
	</sect2>
	
	<!-- Step 5: Create RTSC for role behavior -->
	<sect2><title>Step 5: Create RTSC for role behavior</title>
		<para>
			Now we want to describe the roles’ behavior by assigning RTSCs.
			These RTSCs have to be created first.
		</para>
		<para>
			Therefore, create a RTSC diagram with the name "role_master.realtimestatechart_diagram".
			In the editor that opens in a new tab we can now define our first RTSC.
			In the upper left corner of the drawing surface you can see a small rectangle.
			That is our RTSC. Select it and make it a little bigger.
			Press F2 to change the name and set it to "rtsc_role_master".
		</para>
		<para>
			As said before this RTSC shall describe the behavior of the role "master"
			of our delegation pattern.
			Therefore, click on the rectangle and take a look into the Properties View.
			Within the category "General" you can find the property "Behavioral Element".
			Of course choose "Role Delegation.master". Now the master role of our pattern is 
			linked to this RTSC.
		</para>
		<para>
			Moreover the RTSC needs a clock.
			To add clocks click on the Property "Clocks" within the category "Misc".
			In the value field click on the button "…".
			A dialog opens that looks similar to the data type dialog seen before.
			Analogously create a new clock by clicking on "Create" and name it "c_timeout".	
		</para>
		<para>
			Now we need some states.
			Therefore, click on "State" in the palette and then click into the
			RTSC and name the created state "Inactive".
			This state shall be our initial state for this RTSC.
			Within the Properties View under "General" change the property "Initial" to true.
			Immediately the state is illustrated as an initial state.
		</para>
		<para>
			Now create a second state named "Waiting".
			This state shall have a clock invariant.
			To add one, select the state and under "Misc" in the Properties View select
			"Invariants" and click on "…".
			By clicking on "Create" within the new window a new clock constraint is added.
			Change the properties as follows to create one of the form 
			c_timeout &lt; 1000 :
			<itemizedlist mark='bullet'>
	      		<listitem><para>
	   				<emphasis role="bold">Bound:</emphasis> 1000
	   			</para></listitem>
	   			<listitem><para>
	      			<emphasis role="bold">Clock:</emphasis> Clock rtsc_role_master: c_timeout
	      		</para></listitem>
	      		<listitem><para>
	      			<emphasis role="bold">Operator:</emphasis> LESS
	      		</para></listitem>
	      	</itemizedlist>
	      	The RTSC should look like this now:
	      	<figure id="img:step012">
			<mediaobject>
      			<imageobject>
 	     			<imagedata fileref="User Guide/images/tutorial/tutorialStep012.png" scale="120"/>
      			</imageobject>
			</mediaobject>
			</figure>
			At this point we need some transitions between the two states.
			To add a transition select "Transition" in the palette and click on the state
			in which the transition should start, keep the mouse button pressed and drag
			the cursor to the state in which the transition should end.
			Add a transition from "Inactive" to "Waiting".
			The priority of the transition is chosen in the order you create the transitions,
			but you can also change it in the Properties View under "Misc".
			Here we want the priority to be 1.
			The transition shall carry a clock reset for the clock "c_timeout".
			Select the transition.
			Within the Properties View and the category "Clock" you can find the property
			"Clock Resets". Click on "…" of this property and a dialog pops up again. 
			Select the clock "c_timeout" and click on "Add" to add the chosen clock to the reset list.
			This can be seen in the following screenshot:
			<figure id="img:step013">
			<mediaobject>
      			<imageobject>
 	     			<imagedata fileref="User Guide/images/tutorial/tutorialStep013.png" scale="100"/>
      			</imageobject>
			</mediaobject>
			</figure>
			Furthermore the created transition from "Inactive" to "Waiting" should raise a message event.
			For that select the transition and in the Properties View within the category
			"Raise MessageEvent" the property "Instance Of" must be set. Select "Message Type order"
			to raise the message "order()" we defined a few steps before.
			You can choose this message type, because we set the behavior of the RTSC to the "master"
			role of our delegation pattern and this role has got the "Master2Slave" Message Interface
			as Sender Message Interface.
		</para>
		<para>
			Now create three transitions from "Waiting" to "Inactive" with the following properties:
			<itemizedlist mark='bullet'>
	      		<listitem><para>
	   				Transition 1
	   				<itemizedlist mark='bullet'>
	      				<listitem><para>
	      					Set the priority of this transition to 1.
	   					</para></listitem>
	   					<listitem><para>
							Add a clock constraint by clicking on "..." under "Clock --> Clock Constraint"
							analogously to adding a clock reset with the following properties:
							<itemizedlist mark='bullet'>
	      						<listitem><para>
	      							<emphasis role="Bold">Bound:</emphasis> 1000
	      						</para></listitem>
	      						<listitem><para>
	      							<emphasis role="Bold">Clock:</emphasis> c_timeout
	      						</para></listitem>	
	      						<listitem><para>
	      							<emphasis role="Bold">Operator:</emphasis> GREATER_OR_EQUAL
	      						</para></listitem>	
	      					</itemizedlist>				   						
	   					</para></listitem>
	   				</itemizedlist>
	   			</para></listitem>
	   			<listitem><para>
	   				Transition 2
	   				<itemizedlist mark='bullet'>
	      				<listitem><para>
	      					Set the priority of this transition to 2.
	   					</para></listitem>
	   					<listitem><para>
							Add a Trigger Message Event	of Message Type "fail" analogously
							to adding a Raise Message Event.				
	   					</para></listitem>
	   				</itemizedlist>
	   			</para></listitem>
	   			<listitem><para>
	   				Transition 3
	   				<itemizedlist mark='bullet'>
	      				<listitem><para>
	      					Set the priority of this transition to 3.
	   					</para></listitem>
	   					<listitem><para>
							Add a Trigger Message Event	of Message Type "done".
	   					</para></listitem>
	   				</itemizedlist>
	   			</para></listitem>
	      	</itemizedlist>
	      	Your diagram should look like this now:
	      	<figure id="img:step014">
			<mediaobject>
      			<imageobject>
 	     			<imagedata fileref="User Guide/images/tutorial/tutorialStep014.png" scale="120"/>
      			</imageobject>
			</mediaobject>
			</figure>
			When you now open the delegation pattern you can see within the properties of the "master"
			role that the behavior is set to "Real-Time Statechart rtsc_role_master" automatically.
			Also the red X at the role should be gone.
		</para>
		<para>
			Anyway, what did we do now?
			Generally, we created a RTSC that describes the behavior of the role "master"
			of our delegation pattern.
			But what does this RTSC describe exactly.
			It says that a master role  is either in the state "Inactive" or "Waiting".
			"Inactive" stands for the status the role did not delegate any work to the slave role.
			"Waiting" stand for the status the role did delegate some work and is waiting for an
			answer of the slave.
			The master delegates work by raising the message order().
			Now it has to wait for the slave, which is either sending done() if the work was successful
			or else fail(). If the master gets theses messages it changes its state to "Inactive" again.
			Furthermore the clock constraint we created has the consequence that if the slave
			does not answer within 1000 seconds the master also switches to "Inactive".
		</para>
		<para>
			Now we have to define a RTSC for the role "slave".
			The RTSC for the role "slave" is created analogously to the generation of the RTSC
			for the "master" role.
			That is why we do not describe it again in detail.
			Build it up on your own by taking the following screenshot
			of the RTSC as a reference:
			<figure id="img:step015">
				<mediaobject>
      				<imageobject>
 	     				<imagedata fileref="User Guide/images/tutorial/tutorialStep015.png" scale="120"/>
      				</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</figure>
			Your delegation pattern should now be free of violations of constraints.
		</para>
	</sect2>
	
	<!-- Step 6: Create Atomic Components for Software and GPS -->
	<sect2><title>Step 6: Create Atomic Components for Software and GPS</title>
		<para>
			Now we want to start specifying the BeBots.
			Therefore we have to create two Atomic Components.
		</para>
		<para>
			Create a new Atomiccomponent Diagram named "bebot_ac".
			Add an Atomic Component by clicking on "AtomicComponent" in the palette and then
			clicking into the drawing surface.
			Name it "BeBot_SW". This component will describe how the BeBot works internally.
		</para>
		<para>
			Add a Hybrid Port to this Atomic Component by clicking on "HybridPort" in the palette
			and then clicking on the Atomic Component.
			Name it "position".
			Select the Hybrid Port and set the type to XYPosition by selecting this in the Properties
			View under "Misc --> Type".
			Make sure that the port is an IN-port by checking the property "Kind" under "General".
			Via this port the BeBot will request its position.
		</para>
		<para>
			Add a Discrete Port named "master" analogously.
			This port shall refine the role "master" from our delegation pattern.
			Therefore, you have to change some properties in the Properties View:
			<itemizedlist mark='bullet'>
	      		<listitem><para>
	      			General --> Refines: select "Role Delegation.master"
	      			(to bind the master role of the delegation pattern to this port)
	   			</para></listitem>
	   			<listitem><para>
					MessageInterface --> Receiver Message Interface: select "Slave2Master"				
	   			</para></listitem>
	   			<listitem><para>
					MessageInterface --> Sender Message Interface: select "Master2Slave"				
	   			</para></listitem>
	   			<listitem><para>
					Cardinality --> Lower Bound: set to 0				
	   			</para></listitem>
	   			<listitem><para>
					Cardinality --> Upper Bound: set to 1			
	   			</para></listitem>
	   		</itemizedlist>
	   		The cardinality is chosen to be 0 or 1 because this component will be either
	   		build into a master BeBot or a slave BeBot.
	   		So if we have a master BeBot it will get the master port.
	   		A slave BeBot will not get this port of course.
		</para>
		<para>
			Now create a Discrete Port "slave" with the same properties,
			but commute the Message Interfaces.
			The refinement of course has to be set to "Role Delegation.slave".
		</para>
		<para>
			Save your work.
			As we did not set behaviors for the Atomic Component BeBot_SW and the Discrete Ports,
			we are again getting some red Xs, but we will care about them later.
		</para>
		<para>
			Now create a new Atomic Component named "GPS" with the following properties:
			<itemizedlist mark='bullet'>
	      		<listitem><para>
	      			Make the component a continuous component by setting it under "General --> Component Type".
	   			</para></listitem>
	   			<listitem><para>
					Add a Continuous OUT-Port named "position" of type "XYPosition".
	   			</para></listitem>
	   			<listitem><para>
					Add a Continuous IN-Port named "gps" of type "XYPosition".			
	   			</para></listitem>
	   		</itemizedlist>
	   		This component will be in charge of computing the position of the BeBot.
		</para>
		<para>
			Save your work. Your Atomic Component Diagram should look like this now:
			<figure id="img:step016">
				<mediaobject>
      				<imageobject>
 	     				<imagedata fileref="User Guide/images/tutorial/tutorialStep016.png" scale="120"/>
      				</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</figure>
		</para>
	</sect2>
	
	<!-- Step 7: Create a Structure Component for the BeBot -->
	<sect2><title>Step 7: Create a Structure Component for the BeBot</title>
		<para>
			Once we have defined our Atomic Components,
			we now can define the Structure of our BeBot as a whole by creating a Structured Component.
			Therefore, create a new Structured Component Diagram with the name "bebot".
		</para>
			Add a new Structured Component by clicking on "StructuredComponent"
			in the palette and then clicking into the drawing surface. Name it "BeBot".
			Because this component shall embed both atomic components we created and these were of different types
			this structured component has to be of the component type "hybrid component".
			Set this within the properties of the structured component "BeBot".
		<para>
			Add a Component Part by selecting "ComponentPart" from the palette and clicking
			into the BeBot component. A new Component Part is generated.
			Now you have to set the type. For that in the Properties View select
			"General --> Component Type --> BeBot_SW" to set the type to the atomic component "BeBot_SW" 
			defined before. Name the component "software".
		</para>
		<para>
			Add another Component Part of the type "GPS" with the name "gps" analogously.
		</para>
		<para>
			When you save this diagram now it shows the same errors at the Atomic Component Diagram,
			because the Atomic Component is contained in the current diagram.
			These errors will disappear as soon as we define a behavior for it.
		</para>
		<para>
			Your Diagram should look like this at the moment:
			<figure id="img:step017">
				<mediaobject>
      				<imageobject>
 	     				<imagedata fileref="User Guide/images/tutorial/tutorialStep017.png" scale="120"/>
      				</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</figure>
			Connect the "position" ports of both components by an assembly.
		</para>
		<para>
			Create a Discrete Port "Slave" at the border of the component "BeBot".
			Set the Receiver Message Interface to "Master2Slave" and the Sender Message Interface to
			"Slave2Master".
		</para>
		<para>
			Create a Discrete Port "Master" but with commuted Message Interfaces.
		</para>
		<para>
			Connect the Ports "Master" and "master" by a Delegation by clicking on "Delegation"
			in the palette and drag and drop from "Master" to "master".
			Do the same with the "Slave" and "slave" ports. Now the ports of the "BeBot_SW"
			component are delegated to appropriate ports of the Structured Component.
		</para>
		<para>
			Now create a ContinuousPort "Gps" at the border of the component "BeBot" and connect
			it with a delegation to "gps".
		</para>
		<para>
			Save your work. Now even more Xs are shown.
			That is because we did not define any behavior of these components and ports,
			but this will be changed in a few steps.
		</para>
	</sect2>
	
	<!-- Step 8: RTSCs describing the behavior of the ports -->
	<sect2><title>Step 8: RTSCs describing the behavior of the ports</title>
		<para>
			We start with creating RTSCs for the Ports "master", "slave" and "position".
			The port "gps" does not need any behavior, because it is continuous.
		</para>
		<para>
			Create three RTSC diagrams with name "port_master", "port_slave" and "port_position".
			Name the RTSCs of the diagrams "rtsc_port_master" and so on.
			That is all for the moment. The rest of the definition of these diagrams will be done later,
			because they will be embedded into another RTSC.
		</para>
	</sect2>
	
	<!-- Step 9: RTSCs describing the behavior of the Atomic Component BeBot_SW -->
	<sect2><title> Step 9: RTSCs describing the behavior of the Atomic Component BeBot_SW</title>
		<para>
			Now we want to define the behavior of the software of a BeBot.
			Therefore, create a RTSC Diagram with name "component_bebot-sw".
			Name the statechart itself "rtsc_component_bebot-sw".
		</para>
		<para>
			In the Properties View set the Behavioral Element to "Atomic Component BeBot_SW".
			The software of a BeBot needs an attribute for the current position.
			Hence, add an attribute by clicking on "…" of the property "Attributes".
			In the new window click on "Create" to add a new attribute to the attribute list.
			Set the properties to:
			<itemizedlist mark='bullet'>
	      		<listitem><para>
	      			Name: pos_xy
	   			</para></listitem>
	   			<listitem><para>
					Type: Array Data Type XYPosition
	   			</para></listitem>
	   		</itemizedlist>
	   		Click "OK".
		</para>
		<para>
			To keep track of the diagram we create one superstate for the RTSC.
			Therefore, add a state and name it "bebotsw_main" and change the "Initial" property to true.
		</para>
		<para>
			Now we need three channels for the synchronization of the regions that we create in a moment.
			Select the state and click on "…" of the property "Misc --> Channels". Click on "Create" to add a channel.
			Create three channels with the following properties:
			<itemizedlist mark='bullet'>
	      		<listitem><para>
	      			First channel:
	      			<itemizedlist mark='bullet'>
	      				<listitem><para>
	      					Name: driveTo
	   					</para></listitem>
	   					<listitem><para>
							Parameters: Add a parameter with name "target" of type "XYPosition" like adding attributes to a RTSC
	   					</para></listitem>
	   				</itemizedlist>
	   			</para></listitem>
	   			<listitem><para>
					Second channel:
					<itemizedlist mark='bullet'>
	      				<listitem><para>
	      					Name: success
	   					</para></listitem>
	   				</itemizedlist>
	   			</para></listitem>
	   			<listitem><para>
	   				Third channel:
	   				<itemizedlist mark='bullet'>
	      				<listitem><para>
	      					Name: failure
	   					</para></listitem>
	   				</itemizedlist>
	   			</para></listitem>
	   		</itemizedlist>
			Click "OK". Now you see the list of channels inside the state "bebotsw_main".
			In total our superstate needs four regions, one for each port of the atomic component "BeBot_SW"
			and one describing the internal behavior itself.	
		</para>
		<para>
			Add a region to the superstate by selecting "Region" from the palette and clicking into the state.
			Name it "r_position". This region shall be the part describing the behavior of the position port. 
			In the step before we already created empty RTSCs for the ports. Hence, we add these RTSCs instead of creating new ones. 
			Click on the region name and take a look at the Properties View.
			The property "Statechart" now has to be changed to "Realtime Statechart rtsc_port_position". 
			Now we have added the statechart of "port_position.realtimestatechart_diagram" to the region.
			Set the behavior of this RTSC of region "r_position" to "Hybrid Port position".
			As described before add an attribute with the name "IN_position" of type "XYPosition" and a clock "c_period".
			Now add a state with the name "Idle" and make it an initial state.
			Add a clock invariant within the property "Misc --> Invariants" of the form "c_period &lt; 50".
			Now add a self transition for "Idle" and add the following properties for this transition:
			<itemizedlist mark='bullet'>
		      	<listitem><para>
	      			Clock Reset for "c_period"
	   			</para></listitem>
	   			<listitem><para>
					Clock Constraint of the form "c_period &lt;= 50"
	   			</para></listitem>
	   		</itemizedlist>	
	   		Now we want to describe an action performed when this transition is taken.
	   		Therefore, click on "…" of the property "Action --> Expression". Again a window pops up.
	   		From the drop-down list at the upper-left corner select "TextualExpression" and click on "Create".
	   		Set the property "Expression Text" to "pos_xy := IN_position" and "Language" to "java".
	   		This describes that the action is written in Java and the code is found in "Expression Text".
	   		Here we set the attribute "pos_xy" of the superstate to the value of "IN_position",
	   		an attribute of the current region. Click "OK" and now change "Action --> Name" to "position assignment".
		</para>
		<para>
			Your diagram should look like this now:
			<figure id="img:step018">
				<mediaobject>
      				<imageobject>
 	     				<imagedata fileref="User Guide/images/tutorial/tutorialStep018.png" scale="120"/>
      				</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</figure>
			Now add a new region to "bebotsw_main" and name it "r_master".
			Like before change the statechart to "rtsc_port_master" and set the behavior of this RTSC
			of the region to "Discrete Port master" As for the last region add an attribute "currentTask"
			of type "XYPosition" and a clock "c_timeout". Now you have to add a statechart that is exactly
			like the statechart of "role_master". Therefore, create such a statechart.
		</para>
		<para>
			Now we need to add some things. Select the transition from "Inactive" to "Waiting".
			When raising the message "order(target)" we want to bind the parameter "target" of
			the type "XYPosition" to "currentTask". Therefore, click on "…" of "Raise MessageEvent --> Parameter Binding"
			and type "currentTask" into the value of "target". Furthermore we want to do some synchronization.
			Select the transition with priority 2.
			Change the property "Synchronization --> Sync Channel" to "Synchronization Channel failure" and make
			sure that "Synchronization --> Kind" is set to "SEND". Do the same for the transition with priority 3,
			but for the channel "success" and of kind "RECEIVE". Now we refined our behavior definition for a role
			"master" for this port.
		</para>
		<para>
			Your diagram should look like this now:
			<figure id="img:step019">
				<mediaobject>
      				<imageobject>
 	     				<imagedata fileref="User Guide/images/tutorial/tutorialStep019.png" scale="120"/>
      				</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</figure>
			Again, add a new region to "bebotsw_main" and name it "r_slave".
			As you can imagine, we want to define the behavior of the port "slave" in this step.
			Like before change the statechart to "rtsc_port_slave".
			The following steps have to be handled analogously to the description for the last two ports.
			Therefore, this port is only described in notes.
			Try to implement these on your own and if you are not sure look at the description before.
			<itemizedlist mark='bullet'>
	   			<listitem><para>
					Set Behavioral Element to "Discrete Port slave"
	   			</para></listitem>
	   			<listitem><para>
					Create Attribute with name "Target" of type "XYPosition"
	   			</para></listitem>
	   			<listitem><para>
	   				Create the following operation
					<itemizedlist mark='bullet'>
	   					<listitem><para>
							"DriveTo" with parameter "target" of type "XYPosition" and Return Type "Boolean"
	   					</para></listitem>
	   				</itemizedlist>	
	   			</para></listitem>
	   			<listitem><para>
					Add Clock with name "c_work"
	   			</para></listitem>
	   			<listitem><para>
					Add State named "Inactive", make it initial
	   			</para></listitem>
	   			<listitem><para>
	   				Add State named "Working"
					<itemizedlist mark='bullet'>
	   					<listitem><para>
							Add an Invariant of the form "c_work &lt; 800"
	   					</para></listitem>
	   					<listitem><para>
							Add an Entry Action with the following settings
							<itemizedlist mark='bullet'>
	   							<listitem><para>
	   								Name: "driving"
	   							</para></listitem>
	   							<listitem><para>
	   								Entry Action type: "Textual Expression"
	   							</para></listitem>
	   							<listitem><para>
	   								Expression Text: "//todo" (the implementation at this point is not important for this tutorial)
	   							</para></listitem>
	   								Language: "java"
	   						</itemizedlist>
	   					</para></listitem>
	   				</itemizedlist>	
	   			</para></listitem>
	   			<listitem><para>
	   				Add a Transition from "Inactive" to "Working"
					<itemizedlist mark='bullet'>
	   					<listitem><para>
							Priority: 1
	   					</para></listitem>
	   					<listitem><para>
							Add a Clock Reset for "c_work"
	   					</para></listitem>
	   					<listitem><para>
							Add a Trigger Message Event of type "order"
	   					</para></listitem>
	   				</itemizedlist>	
	   			</para></listitem>
	   			<listitem><para>
	   				Add a Transition from "Working" to "Inactive"
					<itemizedlist mark='bullet'>
	   					<listitem><para>
							Priority: 1
	   					</para></listitem>
	   					<listitem><para>
							Add a Raise Message Event of type "done"
	   					</para></listitem>
	   					<listitem><para>
	   						Add a Guard with the settings
							<itemizedlist mark='bullet'>
	   							<listitem><para>
	   								Expression Text: "xy_pos == target"
	   							</para></listitem>
	   							<listitem><para>
	   								Language: "java"
	   							</para></listitem>
	   						</itemizedlist>
	   					</para></listitem>
	   				</itemizedlist>	
	   			</para></listitem>
	   			<listitem><para>
	   				Add another Transition from "Working" to "Inactive"
					<itemizedlist mark='bullet'>
	   					<listitem><para>
							Priority: 2
	   					</para></listitem>
	   					<listitem><para>
							Add a Raise Message Event of type "fail"
	   					</para></listitem>
	   					<listitem><para>
							Add a Clock Constraint of the form "c_work &lt;= 800"
	   					</para></listitem>
	   				</itemizedlist>	
	   			</para></listitem>
	   		</itemizedlist>	
	   		The lower part of your diagram should now look like this:
	   		<figure id="img:step020">
				<mediaobject>
      				<imageobject>
 	     				<imagedata fileref="User Guide/images/tutorial/tutorialStep020.png" scale="120"/>
      				</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</figure>
		</para>
		<para>
			Now we are done with defining the behavior of the ports of the BeBots.
			At this point the Bebots themselves do not have any behavior.
			Hence, we need a fourth region named "r_internalBahavior".
			Create this and name the corresponding statechart "rtsc_internalBehavior".
			Again this step is a little bit boring, because it is very similar to the steps before.
			Nevertheless, it is reasonable for you to fill this statechart with information to practice using the editor.
			Like before this step is only described in notes:
			<itemizedlist mark='bullet'>
	   			<listitem><para>
					Add Attributes
					<itemizedlist mark='bullet'>
	   					<listitem><para>
							taskList of type "XYPositionArray" (this is an array storing all targets the slave should drive to)
	   					</para></listitem>
	   						currentTask of type INT
	   				</itemizedlist>
	   			</para></listitem>
	   			
	   			<listitem><para>
	   				Add States
					<itemizedlist mark='bullet'>
	   					<listitem><para>
							NoJobGiven, initial
	   					</para></listitem>
	   						JobGiven
	   				</itemizedlist>	
	   			</para></listitem>
	   			
	   			<listitem><para>
	   				Add Transitions
					<itemizedlist mark='bullet'>
	   					<listitem><para>
							From "NoJobGiven" to "JobGIven"
							<itemizedlist mark='bullet'>
	   							<listitem><para>
									Set Synchronizations within the Properties View
									<itemizedlist mark='bullet'>
					   					<listitem><para>
											Kind: Send
					   					</para></listitem>
					   					<listitem><para>
											Sync Channel: driveTo
					   					</para></listitem>
					   					<listitem><para>
											ParameterBinding: set the value of the property "target" to "taskList[currentTask]"
					   					</para></listitem>
					   				</itemizedlist>	
	   							</para></listitem>
	   						</itemizedlist>	
	   					</para></listitem>
	   					<listitem><para>
							From "JobGiven" to "NoJobGiven"
							<itemizedlist mark='bullet'>
			   					<listitem><para>
									Priority: 1
			   					</para></listitem>
			   					<listitem><para>
									Synchronization
									<itemizedlist mark='bullet'>
					   					<listitem><para>
											Kind: Receive
					   					</para></listitem>
					   					<listitem><para>
											Channel: success
					   					</para></listitem>
					   				</itemizedlist>	
			   					</para></listitem>
			   					<listitem><para>
									Action
									<itemizedlist mark='bullet'>
					   					<listitem><para>
											Name: "nextTask"
					   					</para></listitem>
					   					<listitem><para>
											Type: Textual Expression
					   					</para></listitem>
					   					<listitem><para>
											Expression Test: "currentTask++"
					   					</para></listitem>
					   					<listitem><para>
											Language: "java"
					   					</para></listitem>
	   								</itemizedlist>	
			   					</para></listitem>
			   				</itemizedlist>	
	   					</para></listitem>
	   					
	   					<listitem><para>
							From "JobGiven" to "NoJobGiven"
							<itemizedlist mark='bullet'>
			   					<listitem><para>
									Priority: 2
			   					</para></listitem>
			   					<listitem><para>
									Synchronization
									<itemizedlist mark='bullet'>
					   					<listitem><para>
											Kind: Receive
					   					</para></listitem>
					   					<listitem><para>
											Channel: failure
					   					</para></listitem>
					   				</itemizedlist>	
			   					</para></listitem>
			   				</itemizedlist>	
	   					</para></listitem>
	   				</itemizedlist>	
	   			</para></listitem>
	   		</itemizedlist>	
	   		The lower part of your diagram should now look like this:
	   		<figure id="img:step021">
				<mediaobject>
      				<imageobject>
 	     				<imagedata fileref="User Guide/images/tutorial/tutorialStep021.png" scale="120"/>
      				</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</figure>
		</para>
	</sect2>
	<!-- Step 10: The Component Instance Configuration -->
	<sect2><title>Step 10: The Component Instance Configuration</title>
		<para>
			At this point the behavior of our BeBots is defined completely.
			Now we want to create our scenario of the master BeBot sending a task list to the slave BeBot by
			defining a Component Instance Configuration. Therefore, create a Component Instance Configuration
			Diagram named "compInstConfig". What we have to do now is adding instances of our before defined components.
			Hence, add a Structured Component Instance to the diagram. Within the properties as Component Type select 
			"Static Structured Component BeBot". Automatically an instance of this component is created. Now name the
			component "masterBeBot". Connect the "position" ports with an Assembly Instance like we did within the
			Structured Component Diagram before. Furthermore connect the "gps" ports with a Delegation Instance, too.
			Because we defined the master and slave ports with lower bound "0" currently there are no instances for
			these ports. We have to create the needed ones. At the moment we define the master robot.
			Hence, this component instance only needs the master ports and not the slave ports. Click on the "BeBot_SW"
			component part. In the properties click on "…" of "Port Instances" to add ports.
			The master port of this component was a discrete single port. Hence, select "DiscreteSinglePortInstance"
			and click "Create". A new port appears in the list. Select this port and set the "Port Type" to "Discrete
			Port master". Set the name to "master". The remaining properties are filled automatically.
			Now do the same for the "Master" port of the structured component instance "masterBeBot" and connect
			the master ports with a delegation instance.
		</para>
		<para>
			Now our master BeBot is complete and should look like this:
			<figure id="img:step022">
				<mediaobject>
      				<imageobject>
 	     				<imagedata fileref="User Guide/images/tutorial/tutorialStep022.png" scale="120"/>
      				</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</figure>
		</para>
		<para>
			Now we need the slave BeBot. This BeBot is built up almost equally. The only differences are:
			<itemizedlist mark='bullet'>
				<listitem><para>
					The name should be "slaveBeBot", of course.
				</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>
					Instead of the master ports we now have to add slave ports.
				</para></listitem>
			</itemizedlist>	
			The rest is equally to the master BeBot. Create this instance. It should look like this:
			<figure id="img:step023">
				<mediaobject>
      				<imageobject>
 	     				<imagedata fileref="User Guide/images/tutorial/tutorialStep023.png" scale="120"/>
      				</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</figure>
		</para>
		<para>
			The last step is to connecting the "Master" and the "Slave" port of both BeBots
			to enable communication between these two BeBots. Now our component instance configuration is finished.
			Altogether it should look like this:
			<figure id="img:step024">
				<mediaobject>
      				<imageobject>
 	     				<imagedata fileref="User Guide/images/tutorial/tutorialStep024.png" scale="120"/>
      				</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</figure>
		</para>
		<para>
			 Now there is only one thing left: The Deployment.
		</para>
	</sect2>
	<!-- Step 11: The Deployment -->
	<sect2><title>Step 11: The Deployment</title>
		<para>
			At this point we want to link the software we created up to now to hardware.
			Therefore, create a Deployment Diagram named "deployment".
		</para>
		<para>
			Within the Properties View set the Name of the diagram to "deployment" and select
			as Component Instance Configuration the before created "Component Instance Configuration compInstConfig".
		</para>
		<para>
			Now we can define the deployment. We need two Hardware Nodes, one for the Master and one for the Slave.
			Hence, add two nodes and name them "masterBeBot" and "slaveBeBot".
			For the correct deployment select "Structured Component Instance masterBeBot" resp.
			"Structured Component Instance slaveBeBot" for Deployed Instances within the properties of the nodes.
			The component instances we created before had a GPS port and a Master resp. Slave port.
			Therefore, add Hardware Ports to the Hardware Nodes. Within the Properties of the Ports you can set
			the "Deployed Port Instance". The Master BeBot needs the Gps1 port and the Master port.
			Analogously the Slave BeBot also needs the Gps1 port and the Slave port. The GPS ports have
			to be in-Ports as preset, but the Master resp. Slave port are in/out-Ports. Hence, set the Property
			"Kind" of the ports to "IN_OUT".
		</para>
		<para>
			Now create a Communication Link between these two ports so that the BeBots can communicate.
			The final deployment should look like this:
			<figure id="img:step025">
				<mediaobject>
      				<imageobject>
 	     				<imagedata fileref="User Guide/images/tutorial/tutorialStep025.png" scale="120"/>
      				</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</figure>
		</para>
		<para>
			At this point this tutorial ends. We created a scenario where one BeBot sends missions to another BeBot. 
			This is a very simple example, but you got to know the most common features of the MechatronicUML Tool Suite.
		</para>
	</sect2>
</sect1>